foreign
so
[Music]
hello everyone good evening good day
welcome to the 59th episode of ask
abhijeet
i hope you are all doing very well
so as you know today is a
session in which i will answer questions
from the comments it's not a live chat
question but it's live of course
so you have you all have uh asked
several hundred very interesting
questions in the comments and i've
picked pulled out a bunch of those
emma and i'm going to be answering those
today but let me first see who all is
here today tonight with us
so let's see who all is there i can see
deepak kumar avinash kumar abhinav
mishra
pratyush iron man chaitu
and
lots lots lots of other people
very nice to see you all thank you for
being here
and let us get into the questions shall
we
so let's start with the first question
what's the first question
okay this is by great me
indus valley food habits where
okay the question is what were the indus
valley civilizations food habits like
was it predominantly rice based or wheat
based
did they used to eat rotis like we do
today
good question so what we have found is
that uh
the uh primary
cereal that was used in this
era of our civilization was
i think it was millet
millet is called bajra in hindi so there
used to be this bajira cultivation there
is also evidence of rice cultivation
that is as old as the rice cultivation
that has been found in china so there
was rice there was millet or bajra
and there were other cereals too i think
but and i'm sure there's wheat as well
so there is also evidence of wheat
cultivation but it's not as old
as the evidence for right or for rice or
millet
so there were
multiple grains that were being used in
this
in this phase of our civilization but if
you look at the primary
grain
cereal i think it was the millet the
bajra
and
and they have also found okay we don't
know whether they used to eat rotis like
we do today
because rotis are you know flat and very
thin and they don't you know you can't
preserve them over several thousand
years
and therefore we don't have evidence of
whether they used to eat
our ancestors used to eat rotis or not
at the time what we have found is
evidence of ladoos
these are balls
of
multiple grain grains so it's a
multi-grain ball that they found they in
one of the regions they one in one of
the archaeological sites they found
a
remnants of these ladoos that had been i
think kind of fossilized in some way not
really fossilized but they somehow got
preserved
and the analysis analysis was done and
it was found that there are multiple
grains in that in those ladoos
and there could be other ingredients
like sugar ghee etc also which i'm not
very sure about but multiple grains were
present
and there is evidence of
of
dairy products we're being used in this
uh
in this time time frame
as well as there is evidence i mean i
think one of the oldest dishes that they
have been able to reconstruct was
found from the residue of
of an ancient pot in which they found
that somebody had cooked a mixture of a
mixture of ginger and eggplant
brinjal
so yeah we can actually reconstruct some
of these things
so that's the kind of diet there was
there i'm sure there was meat
consumption too in some parts and all
that
some people have claimed that there was
a
consumption of cattle but that is very
flimsy and
spurious kind of evidence you know but
i'm sure there was consumption of meat
as well
at least among some people so that's the
kind of food habits we had
in the so-called indus valley
civilization which is
one of the phases of our
civilization indian civilization
so good question to start off with let's
see the second the question
sanchit asks did bhaskaracharya discover
the concept of gravity or was it isaac
newton
see
uh bhaskaracharya did uh write about
gravity
he called it gurudwakarshan
and the concept was very clear that you
know the concept of gravity that we are
familiar with was known to him
and he was not the first indian or the
first person to to
to discuss or write about gravitation
i think the shattapata brahmana which is
an ancient vedic text it is one of the
commentaries on the white yejur veda
this text also
uh speaks about gravity and the and the
attractive force that exists between uh
massive bodies massive objects or with
between objects with mass
so the concept was known to indians
so you cannot credit isaac newton for
discovering the concept of gravity but
when it comes to the formulation of
gravity as an inverse square law isaac
newton was the first person to do that
to create to give us the mathematical
representation
uh of the gravitational force and
potential
so that is something isaac newton did
but the
law of gravitation the the concept of
gravity was very well known to ancient
indians and when we talk about the
shatta pata brahmana people say it's
about 400 500 bce but that is absolute
nonsense because this text
references the drying up of the
saraswati river which happened around
1900 or 1500 bce at least it's when the
drying up of the river
was complete
but
the drying process took a very long time
maybe several thousand years so
it's clear that the brahmana goes back
at least a
minimum four thousand years before today
so that's how long we have known about
the concept of gravity and this lot that
there's a lot of texts that we have lost
of course
but as far as we know isaac newton is
the first person who gave us the inverse
square
law of gravity the mathematical
formulation
which came to him in a flat of in a
flash of inspiration apparently when an
apple fell fall fell onto his head
so bhaskar acharya was one in a long
line of indian scientists who was aware
about gravity bhaskarachary was
of course
one of the
great
ancient indian scientists so
that's the answer
okay the warrior says
as an aspiring researcher in physics how
shall i start my career in india because
next year i'll be joining undergraduate
courses
uh well you have to get yourself a
bachelor's degree and a master's degree
in whatever
specialization of physics you are
interested in
and then you go on to have a phd that's
how you do research that's the
conventional way of doing research
unfortunately in india the academic
scene is not very good i mean
do you hear of any real research being
done in india in the field of physics
and you don't even need labs to do
theoretical physics research right
all you need is your brain a pencil and
a pen and paper but you don't see any
real research happening in this country
because well the academic system
unfortunately is such that it promotes
mediocre minds and it destroys talented
people so if you really want to do
research in physics i will give you the
right advice i'll say get out of this
country
go abroad
where actual research happens and then
when you are an established researcher
and maybe
10 20 years down the line when india is
a better place to do research and then
you can come back and contribute to the
country
but if you want to establish yourself as
a researcher i think the best way is to
first get yourself a bachelor's degree
the so-called undergraduate degree then
a master's degree and then you should go
for a phd
so that is the conventional way of doing
it of course you can also do some other
work and you can keep doing research in
your free time that also works so for
that you don't need any degrees
so that is the course of action there's
a couple of courses of action you could
take unfortunately there is no real
research happening in this country all
the academicians they are glorified
teachers that's all they do and that do
they do very poorly i'm not saying
they're all like this there are a few
gems here and there of course but they
are in a very small minority
the average academician the average
professor is
well i don't have any kind
term to use for them so
you you get what i mean right
so that's a deal right
how to become a good mathematician is
what karan nalavat asks
so ask yourself how do you become a good
musician
let's say you're starting from scratch
you want to become you know become a
good guitar player how to do that you do
it through practice and dedication
how do you become a good
sports person
practice dedication hard work
how do you become a good cook chef
practice dedication hard work you need
to be interested in that you need to be
passionate about that
similarly mathematics is a skill one
acquires
uh it is not just a skill but
problem solving problems etc as you go
as you advance in your mathematical
career is a skill that you need to learn
through a lot of repetition through a
lot of problem solving exercises
so to become a good mathematician you
start with the very fundamentals of
mathematics
addition subtraction multiplication
division
fractions and then you progress further
and further up once you have a
if you have a strong foundation
mathematics is the easiest thing in the
world
mathematics is something everyone is
scared of but it's actually the easiest
thing in the world to do if your
foundations are right unfortunately our
academic system
ensures that our foundations are
terrible and that's why we can't
progress further in mathematics when it
comes to algebra trigonometry geometry
calculus and so on because it sounds
very complicated but that's the right
way to approach mathematics start with
the very fundamentals very basics
spend your time
mastering those and then slowly progress
further and it will all depend on how
quickly you're able to pick up
and absorb and retain concepts
and of course you will need a lot of
practice hard work dedication just like
any other skill so that's how you become
a good mathematician you need some uh
you need books which give you lots of
practice in solving problems
and then you need to be
able to retain new concepts and just
progress
that's how you do it
okay kushagra says one of the main
reasons for people converting to
christianity is that the missionaries
provide free education
how can we develop a system where
children from not privileged to class
can get the education in a dharmic way
well actually today the scene the
situation is such that if you want to
get admission to a missionary school you
have to pay huge amounts of money unless
you are convert right
it's that kind of thing so today
missionary schools have become
prestigious things
everyone wants to send their kids to a
convent school what they call what they
call a convent school or a missionary
school where they get this education
which also
brainwashes the children into
you know other
things so initially the
the mechanism they used for converting
people in china and in india
was to create enormous poverty in the
country and then offer people
the chinese you know i i did i i showed
this in
one of the previous one of the older
episodes the chinese they called such
converts rice christians
because the christian missionaries they
first of all the europeans had created
this terrible poverty in china
and then the missionaries
who were forced upon the country
they would convert people
in exchange i mean they would offer
bags of rice to to starving chinese
peasants in exchange for them converting
to christianity so the chinese had a
term for these people rice christians
that's what the chinese used to call
them
and the similar techniques have been
used in india as we know
and
after the macaulayan system was imposed
in india you had to go through the
british western education system you had
to abandon the indian education system
was was destroyed
and then the most prestigious education
was was the one that was found in these
missionary schools convent schools
whatever you call them
so what is the solution to this today
also it's it's going on the most
prestigious schools where they teach you
the most polished english etc are the
convent schools missionary schools and
parents they they want their kids to
succeed in this country in india if you
want to succeed you need to be able to
speak english at a high level of
competence with a certain accent only
then will you be impressive in your in
your job interviews and all that so
parents they are forced to send their
kids to these
uh
missionary schools where kids get
brainwashed into hating their culture
and all that we know that
what is the solution the solution is
very simple i've spoken about this in
any civilized society
education and health care must be
completely free
that's the solution
we are all paying taxes either directly
or indirectly many of us pay income
taxes in the in the country of india i
mean everybody is supposed to pay income
tax uh not everyone does farmers don't
pay anything for instance but
many of the indians many of the indians
pay income tax and even if people are
dodging income tax or whatever whenever
you buy something there is gst on it
there is to be vat earlier now is gst so
every time you purchase either a service
or any goods you are paying tax to the
government
there are road taxes there are all kinds
of building taxes god knows what stamp
duty it's it's a collection mechanism
right they are collecting taxes from you
all of you
so why why are the people of india
paying taxes to get some benefit from
the government right
the government is supposed to serve the
nation and the people in the long
and ensure the long-term prosperity and
security
of the people
so i
i am of the firm opinion that in any
civilized society like we had in this
country in the past
education and healthcare should be
completely free even after the dominion
status in 1947
yeah
even after that for some time the the
so-called
princely states were still in existence
and it is known for a fact that even
after 1947 for a brief period of time in
these princely states you used to get
free education and free health care if
you felt sick or something there were
government of hospitals that you could
go to where you would get free
treatment if you were hospitalized they
would even give you free food and this
was available to everybody
everybody every single person who was
a citizen of the princely state and
similarly for education education was
always free it was always subsidized by
the state
the teachers etc were all given salaries
and every in their livelihoods by the
state by the kings and queens
but after independence after the
dominion status of 1947
yeah
after that what's happened is that
they've turned education into a business
they've turned healthcare into a
business that's why
and that's why you have the situation in
this country you cannot
turn education and healthcare into
business
right that is just contrary to every uh
concept of civilization every
ideal every principle of being a
civilized society
so that's what needs to happen
if you if the i'm i'm not saying it
should happen tomorrow it's not feasible
to do it tomorrow india needs to first
become
a middle-income country let's give it
another 10 years once our total
uh national gdp crosses 10 12 billion uh
sorry trillion dollars then the
government can certainly take up this
this step in it's a vast
subcontinent-sized country so it will
take some doing but that's what the
government is for it's their job to do
this
and the government has succeeded so
brilliantly in vaccinating over a
billion people
more than uh i think more than 70 80
percent of indians have got at least one
dose of vaccination and more than 30
percent have got the second dose as well
so the government machinery can be
deployed
very effectively
in in doing these things and similarly
you can
make
education and health care also reach the
masses once india is sufficiently
sufficient sufficiently uh prosperous in
terms of
per capita gdp
so that's what needs to happen india
needs to
in the past i mean
throughout
india's civilizational history we we
have always
provided healthcare and education for
free to everybody
so that's what we need to go back to and
then all these problems will go away
right so that's what needs to happen
hopefully someday
soon okay harshit says
why did the british take
a great deal great amount of effort
in creating the asi the archaeological
survey of india and in historical
research of indic texts
can it be termed as their single
selfless contribution to india since it
helped us
to explore our glorious past and debunk
the debunk the myths of white supremacy
or were there any hidden interests
so good question very good question now
i would not agree that it helped us
debunk explore our glorious past and
debunk
the white supremacy the let's understand
the agenda
the british had a single singular
purpose
in occupying our
our country
undivided india they came to india for
the purpose of enriching themselves of
extracting wealth out of india
and turning india and india into into
their
well
into their their uh
vasal state
of sorts so their singular purpose was
to enrich themselves they did not come
to india for the purpose of philanthropy
they did not come to india to uplift
indians out of poverty they created the
poverty and destitution that you you see
even today in the country they destroyed
the very fabric of indian society so
then what was the need to do this aid to
create the asi and
do all the historical research and find
try to uncover the history of india
well
please go to the british museum please
go to western museums and you will see
these museums full
of priceless indian
treasures
the primary purpose of the asi
was to find all of india's ancient
historical monuments and find everything
of value
in these monuments and then take out
all the beautiful sculptures the murtis
the idols
and everything else that could be
that would be considered in the west to
be a collector's item or something that
would be that would be nice and
ornamental and decorative in a rich
person's house
so these antiques these priceless indian
treasures were
carted away
to britain
where they were either either put in
museums or they made their way into
people's into rich collectors
collections
so that was the primary purpose of the
asi and it you know
even after 1947 the asi has operated in
the same manner
there are lots of archaeological sites
that
technically and officially fall under
the asi's protection they will not allow
you to go there and take photographs
they will prevent you from taking videos
it is your heritage they're talking
about but they will not allow you to
take photographs there or take videos
there because apparently i mean i don't
understand the logic for it
and they will charge you money if you
want to enter the monument right
and yet they will not take care of the
monuments yes they will they they spend
a lot of time they spend a lot of time
developing the and then
restoring turkic monuments and british
monuments
but india's priceless heritage
the pre-invasion the preoccupation
heritage of india is totally neglected
and much of it is actively still being
pilfered away and it's making its way
into the west i had shown in the
previous episode what's happening in
rocky and other places it has been
reported many times in the indian media
that the site is being looted
and i have shown in on this website
called vatican.com that this
priceless indian heritage
five six thousand year old heritage all
these various items that have been
stolen from
indus valley and saraswati valley uh
archaeological sites it is being
auctioned off online it is in the hands
of western collectors so that is what
the asi is still overseeing today
you see you hear you you read these news
reports every every other day of some
priceless idol some murthy being stolen
from some temple which is in the under
the asis jurisdiction
so the asi is very much still a colonial
institution
right so there was no selfless
contribution to india in any way in any
shape or form from the british it was
all done to enrich themselves to take
out everything of value from india
and that's what they did so that is the
reason why the british created the asi
and why did they study indian texts
why did they learn sanskrit they learned
sanskrit so that they could read temple
records
india's temples
they have been receiving donation for
donations from devotees from pilgrims
from kings from queens even from foreign
kings and queens for thousands of years
india's temples were fabulously wealthy
today they are all empty where did the
money go
and uh and i'm i'm so glad that the shri
ananta padmanama swami temple in kerala
shri padmanava swami temple in kerala
was able to escape the british gaze it
contains the at least
at least minimum 1 trillion
worth of treasure in today's money
minimum i think it's like several times
more and it's clear that this this
has been donated over several thousand
years
right so that's the reason why the
british wanted to learn
sanskrit and uh
read our ancient texts so that they
could figure out which temple contains
how much treasure right
instead of going and examining
everything just get the books
and study it and then then decide which
temple to loot
so that's what happened most of the
temples that survived the turkic
occupation of india were in southern
india
most of them are empty of their
treasures today
right
and
people will construe this in a different
way that you know the temples were
hoarding india's wealth
the this is brahminical oppression the
brahmins who control the temple were
holding india's wealth and that's why
india was so poor and the temples were
so rich such utter nonsense
all this wealth was donated by the
people of india india was the most
prosperous society on the surface of the
planet and indians the temples were
cultural centers they were centers of
culture civilization and they were
centers of education
and people donated money and wealth and
everything else to the temples in order
to maintain the upkeep of the temples
and of course there was a surplus
donation which the temples could not use
because people were devout and they
wanted to support the temples and they
just as a consequence they just stored
everything within the temple
and that's why the temples were so
fabulously rich because india was the
richest civilization on earth
so that's why the british
learned sanskrit and tried to decipher
and read our ancient texts so that they
could figure out everywhere there was
treasure in the country that's the only
reason
okay why didn't the british invade tibet
when they already had presence across
india and why did the soviet union
not do that when they had presence
across asia
also is if there is a power in tibet
which secured their sovereignty from
these two big empires then why and how
did china succeed in invading tibet okay
it's a convoluted question but good
question good question
so let's do a cost benefit analysis of a
british invasion of tibet let's say
you're british let's say you are the
person in charge of
the occupation the the illegal
occupation of india
the british raj okay
why would it invade debt what will you
gain from it cost benefit analysis tibet
is a vast
plateau
it's an enormous region
right to reach tibet you have to cross
the himalayas and you have to then
survive in this harsh environment it's
it's a barren place it's mostly empty
uh
there are no treasures there to be to be
looted
there's nothing to be gained from there
so for the british it would be it would
make no sense whatsoever to spend so
much effort
invest so so many uh personnel troops
etc in invading
a land where there is nothing to be
gained
so why would they invade tibet what
would they gain from it invading india
made so much sense because well they
enrich themselves at the expense of
india that's why the west is so
fabulously wealthy today because all the
wealth that was taken out of places like
india and africa mainly india
so there was a great deal of
benefit
in occupying india with respect to the
cost of occupying india in the case of
tibet there was nothing to be gained you
just gain
control over an enormous territory where
there's very little population there is
no
wealth there is no treasure nothing the
real wealth was spiritual
over there that's that's what you had so
there was no point for the british in
doing that when it came to the ussr
again what would they gain from it
they would gain a big piece of almost
almost empty territory
uh so that's the thing right now why did
the chinese
invade tibet and annex it
illegally forcibly well the chinese have
geopolitical reasons for doing that
tibet is the source of the main of most
of the major rivers in asia
and by
occupying tibet the chinese get to
control the source of all the water
and that is one of the major reasons and
of course there are minerals and other
resources in tibet which would take long
term occupation and exploitation to uh
benefit from
so the chinese had a clear geopolitical
reason for doing it but and therefore
there is a significant benefit as
opposed
as compared to the cost of invading an
occupying tibet for the chinese but it
did not make sense from a cost-benefit
perspective
to do that for the british or the
soviets
and that's why uh they didn't the
british or the soviets did not
make any real significant moves to in a
real attempt
to
invade and occupy tibet
and about sovereignty how did china
succeed in invading tibet
uh the chinese would not have succeeded
had they not been given significant
assistance by jawaharlal nehru
so the chinese soldiers when they
occupied when they invaded tibet they
were starving they were freezing today
to death they were so far away from from
china
uh
and
the logistics were not working out so
they were starving so what mr nehru the
great shri jawaharlal nehru did he
supplied
thousands of tons of indian rice to the
invading chinese soldiers
and that's why the chinese were able to
successfully
complete their invasion of tibet
so that's why the chinese succeeded in
invading and
occupying tibet and that's why their
occupation
continues
and
tibet was kind of a protectorate of the
british raj and after independence or
after the dominion status of 1947 that
responsibility passed on to india but mr
nero could not even administer his own
country properly what about tibet
so he he was perfectly happy with the
chinese taking over tibet and the second
reason is that the tibetans were a very
peaceful culture
they believed in non-violence rather too
strongly
i mean there are plenty of examples in
history of buddhist cultures
having strong military and martial
traditions take thailand for instance
they have very strong martial arts
traditions despite being buddhists
they have been
conquerors and invaders in their own
time
the
kings of thailand the chakri dynasty
right
if you look at the other kingdoms for
instance myanmar
they also
see
thailand and myanmar are are a mixture
of buddhist and hindu there's no real
difference like i've said millions of
times
so the the so in thailand in in myanmar
in cambodia laos you have the martial
and military traditions there is nothing
in both the dharma that says you cannot
fight
for your self-defense similarly in japan
which is which used to be a very
devoutly buddhist nation
you had the samurai traditions model
traditions
you had
the bushido code
you had ninjutsu and so much more right
and china was a buddhist nation then the
great monk
bodhidharma who was indian went there he
was he is considered a buddhist monk not
a hindu monk so he went to china and
taught them what is now known as kung fu
so there is nothing in buddhism that
says that you cannot fight for
self-defense or indulge in any kind of
violence for self-preservation the
tibetans kind of forgot that
and they became completely pacifist and
they did not maintain a significant army
and that also is a major reason where
the chinese were able to walk into tibet
once they had the rice that mr nehru
provided them so that's why this
happened
in a nutshell
okay amv spot says why did the turks
destroy non-profitable buildings like
nalanda university when it had nothing
to do with material wealth
see when you are an invader and you
invade and conquer
another
another territory another nation another
culture what you do is you try to
destroy all
possibilities of resistance
so that makes military sense
if there are military installations if
there are military outposts you would go
and destroy them and you would
uh ensure that you
neutralize the the fighting forces the
soldiers and so and so on so forth so it
makes sense as an invader as an occupier
to wipe out to destroy to seek to
destroy
military installations
in any center where any any form
of resistance in the country you have
occupied by force
when it comes to a university
it doesn't have any military purpose
it has a cultural and educational
purpose
and yet these turks went ahead and
destroyed
all of india's universities all of
india's ancient universities great
universities they burned all the
libraries and they beheaded all the
monks
nalanda had more than five thousand
monks who were all beheaded mostly in
one day imagine the scene there
and there were so many other
universities they were all destroyed
and so on and so forth
all of these great universities were
destroyed they were all burned all the
monks were
massacred monks are not a military force
teachers are not military for a military
force students and professors are not a
military force they don't they don't
fight
and yet the turks did this so the
purpose for doing this
was not
it was not a military purpose
it was to uh it was a
well it was to ensure that india's
culture was destroyed and they succeeded
in wiping out all of india's ancient
records of historical records all of
india's ancient texts the ancient
uh guru shisha and gurukul tradition
that had been going on that had been
continuing for thousands of years it's
gone it's all gone now
so they destroyed it
and so the purpose was to destroy indian
culture and indian civilization it was
not a military purpose it was something
much more sinister and evil
so that's what the turks did and we
should never forget that
darshan kothari says the sun is a
burning star but what is it made of
because if anything that keeps on
burning burning will end
so why does the sun have no such end
the sun is a burning star
so when you talk about fire you're
talking about a chemical reaction an
exothermic chemical reaction when you
take a matchstick and set it off
because of with the so what happens is
that
there is a chemical reaction in the
tip of the matchstick
the chemicals ignite
they give off an enormous amount of heat
very localized heat
and it's a chemical reaction it's an
exothermic chemical reaction
so that
changes the chemistry changes as a
result of this chemical reaction and the
output is this what we perceive as fire
so it gives off a great deal of
radiation in form of heat and light so
that is what we see and what we call
fire
and the same applies not only not only
in matchsticks but also when you burn
wood or paper or any substance it's an
exothermic chemical reaction
right so that's what we see on earth
now
in the case of the sun
it is not a chemical reaction that we
are witnessing
it is a thermonuclear
reaction it's a nuclear reaction that
you are witnessing
so
uh
on earth you don't get to see nuclear
reactions
there have been a few nuclear tests that
were done the atmospheric tests that a
few people have been able to witness
most nuclear tests have been done
underground
and the nuclear reactors that power some
of the world's uh
electric supply and also so on these are
these are the nuclear reactions that
happen in those reactors they are
they are insulated they are con confined
in the nuclear reactor so you don't get
to see it the engineers technicians may
be able to see the challenge of
radiation etc but not anything anything
apart from that so
over 99.9 of humanity has never seen a
nuclear reaction on the surface of the
planet
but if you're wondering what a nuclear
reaction looks like
look east in the morning
and see the rising sun
the sun is an enormous nuclear reactor
the fuel that is being
consumed by the nuclear reaction is
hydrogen
so the sun is an enormous enormous ball
it's composed of about 75 percent
roughly hydrogen
about 23 24 helium
and the rest is heavier elements like
oxygen calcium
carbon
and some metals as well these are all
called metals in
astrophysics so the nuclear reaction
that takes place is a fusion reaction
you are fusing two hydrogen atoms to
form a helium atom that's essentially
what's happening in the core
of the sun and that is an extremely an
enormously
energetic
process it's an extremely energetic
reaction
so that is a thermonuclear reaction that
you see every day in the morning every
day in the daytime if you want to see
what a nuclear bomb looks like a
continuously exploding nuclear bomb look
at the sun that is a nuclear reaction so
it's not burning any any wood or any
such thing
uh it's a nuclear reaction that consumes
hydrogen and gives off and the output is
helium
eventually the sun will start running
out of hydrogen
and then the entire
physics will change but that's a
different story
so there is so much hydrogen in the sun
that is being consumed that's why there
is no end
the sun is going to keep on consuming
this hydrogen fuel for at least
i would say the next five billion years
or so until it becomes a red giant and
then the
physics will change
eventually it will die out eventually
but we don't need to worry about that
so in short that's what the sun is it's
not burning actually like the the kind
of fire that we see on earth it's a
nuclear reaction an extremely
energetic
nuclear reaction called nuclear fusion
that you are witnessing
okay
slapstick memes says please tell us
about the pakistan water treaty and how
can we sign out
of it if it's not in india's interests
so what you're referencing is the indus
the so-called indus waters treaty
i think it was signed by the indian
government with pakistan in i think 1960
i think it was done by mr nehru the
great shri jawaharlal nehru
he decided in this treaty to give away
i think eighty percent of the water of
this of the saptasana region
to pakistan india only gets to use 20 of
the waters even though all of the rivers
pass through india before they reach
pakistan the sindhu river the ravi bayas
chennai satellite etc all these rivers
they pass through india and after
passing through india they go into
pakistan
and yet we are giving off giving away 80
of the water to pakistan it's one of the
most unequal treaties in the history of
humankind
it's as if somebody put a gun to your
head and forced you to sign this unequal
treaty and yet it was not the case
india willingly gave up eighty percent
of the water to pakistan
despite being the larger nation and the
more powerful nation that's the kind of
geopolitics our so-called
great statesmen leaders
played
and you can see how much it has harmed
the country so clearly it's not in
india's interest why should we give off
give away so much of our water to the
pakistanis our our sworn enemies why
should we do that
i mean the chinese conquered tibet
primarily for the water because tibet is
the source of
uh
most of the major rivers in asia so the
chinese get to control that water
because they
they control tibet and they have signed
no such treaty with any other asian
nation
they control the water as they wish
and the asian nations have to put up
with that and they have nothing there's
nothing they can do
so what was the need to sign this treaty
with the pakistanis
i think the treaty was brokered by the
imf if i am not mistaken the
international monetary fund or something
like that
so it is
certainly not in india's interests so
how can india sign out of it we can sign
out of it anytime we like there is no
need to adhere to a treaty that is not
in india's interests the the chinese for
instance signed a treaty with the
british when hong kong again become a
part of china that there would be
one or what one nation two systems that
sort of thing
and recently they have reneged on the
treaty they said that we will no longer
uh honor the treaty and now it's one
nation one system
and they are imposing their system on
hong kong and what can the british do
about it it's an
it's international treaty
it's a treaty signed by two between two
nations a bilateral treaty like the
indus waters treaty so if you're strong
enough and if you have sufficient
self-respect then you can always break a
treaty there was this iran nuclear deal
which the americans broke right
they turned their back on it they they
went back on the treaty they refused to
honor the another treaty they then felt
signed so it happens all the time but
you need to have
you need to be a strong nation to be
able to do that so how can india do this
first of all india needs to start
constructing dams on all the rivers
uh
and then we can weaponize it whenever
it's needed when the pakistan is if the
pakistan is in the future
try to play any misadventure with india
we can we can cut off the water so
that's what india needs to do if we just
empty words will not threaten pakistan
because if we said that we will cut off
the water we currently lack the ability
to do that
to actually cut off the water you need
to construct dams on all the rivers
let the pakistanis complain and go
wherever they want to go go to the u.n
go wherever else go to china doesn't
matter if india is strong enough india
can do that so it's something that will
happen i'm sure in the future
india right now needs to build its
economy up to at least 10 trillion
dollars
when
you reach there your military will have
a correspondingly large size and you
will be powerful enough to do such
things so right now india i think the
government of india is focusing
on economic growth but i think
it should also
happen in parallel with other kinds of
uh
progress
anyhow so that's how india can sign out
of the treaty or or you know
declare the treaty null and void
okay aryan chauhan says why after the
first indo-pakistan war on kashmir free
elections have not been conducted till
today
to know what the people of kashmir want
as guided by the united nations
i mean who the hell
is the united nations to guide us
who the hell are they
why do we have to recognize their
authority and everything
and even if you go by the u.n
declaration or whatever it was
it is clearly mentioned in the
declaration
that in order to get this process going
the pakistanis need to first
withdraw from the territories they
occupied in 1947 48
right
so that's what needs to happen
and my my contention is very simple even
pakistan is an illegitimate nation
uh the creation of pakistan was done
against the wishes of the people of
india the people of india were never
consulted
are we willing to give up our ancestral
civilizational territory
are we willing to do that was there a
referendum in india before partition was
accepted no
a small bunch of people
mohandas muhammad ali jinnah jawahar
and the british they got together and
decided to do this
right
there was no referendum
and it clearly did not reflect the will
of the people even the pashtuns were
against it
the pashtuns were clearly against
partisan they wanted a unified india
so uh
pakistan itself is an illegitimate state
it needs to be reintegrated into india
sometime in the future
maybe in the next hundred or so years
it's a long-term process we didn't
need not hurry it too much
so
i would say that there is no need to
ever hold any election in kashmir it is
indian territory it has been india's
territory for thousands of years
and we need to
i mean just carry on with our national
nation building process
there is no need to have any kind of
external interference in india's
internal matters
india if you talk about the kashmir
dispute it is at best a bilateral
dispute
at best so the u.n has no role in this
india will retake gilgam and pakistan
occupied kashmir in due course of time i
would say it will happen in the next
five to ten years it's going to happen
and then you can have all the elections
you want to hold right
so i i the point i would like to make is
that we need to stop
trying to legitimize
external actors like the un and other
four
and other
external actors why do we need their
guidance
are we not capable
of choosing our own path as a as a
culture as a society as a nation as a
civilization
are they somehow superior to us that we
don't have the wisdom that they will
give us the wisdom and the guidance why
do we need that
india needs to be a strong confident
nation that determines its own destiny
so let's let's talk let's stop talking
about the u.n we just need to take back
kashmir
and then you can hold as many elections
as you as you want in kashmir
jain austin the great novelist says
asks whether the fibonacci numbers are
originally from india
yes of course they were called the
pingala number the great mathematician
pingala was most likely the
first person that we know of
who described this series so the
fibonacci series
is a very simple series you take two
numbers you start from zero and one then
you add the two numbers so what is zero
plus one it's one
then you take the last two numbers in
the series which is one and one you add
them you get two then you add two and
one you get three when you add three and
two you get five and so on so forth
that's the fibonacci series so it was it
is one of the simplest series it is a
good app it is a reasonably good
approach approximation of the uh
the fibonacci spiral is a good
approximation of the golden spiral the
golden ratio and so on so this is a
concept that was known in india for a
very very long time it's a very simple
concept it's strange that the
europeans arabs etc never thought of it
right
so this all this knowledge this indian
mathematical knowledge was transmitted
to the west
by the arabs the arabs never hid the
fact that this was indian knowledge
they were very clear about the fact that
this was all indian mathematics and
that's what they called it in their
books
but when these texts made their way into
europe
the europeans
uh tried to conceal where the real the
this was this or whether this
information this knowledge originated
so the decimal system they call it the
arabic numerals
it's actually the indian numerals or the
hindu numerals
today the wikipedia says it's the hindu
arabic numerals or something
it's there's nothing arabic about it
the arabs were just the transmitters to
the west
so the fibonacci series the fibonacci
numbers yes
it's an indian discovery
uh the
earliest known person uh
scientist indian mathematician to write
about this was pingala
so it is more appropriate to call it the
pingala series of the pingala numbers
okay vishal mahajan asks what do you
think about graham hancock's theories
about the amazon rainforest region and
the history of america
before columbus
uh it's an interesting question graham
hancock has been writing about this he
has focused primarily on
the uh americas
and his theory is that uh
so according to mainstream history
uh north america was
uh the first human presence in north
america
according to mainstream history happened
about 13 000 or 14 000 years ago
when the aleutian strait the bearing
strait was frozen over
because of
the last glacial
episode the ice age and therefore humans
were able to cross this bridge this land
bridge
uh walking just walk walk across it
and it's it's quite clear that the
people of the the indigenous
natives the true natives of america
north america and southern america also
are
ethnically quite similar to the people
of of uh
siberia and mongolia right
so it's clear that there was some there
was a significant migration from
eastern asia
into north america and eventually it
made its way all the way into southern
america and south america
so that is the mainstream history so it
says that there was no human habitation
in the americas before about 13 14 000
years before today before that there was
no human presence there so graham
hancock says according to his theory he
says that there was human presence much
before that maybe even a hundred
thousand years before today or even
before that
so that's what he has been claiming
that's what he has been writing about it
is in his books and all and he has been
dismissed for a very long time as a
fringe researcher as a pseudo-historian
and so on
and now what happens is that he is
increasingly getting vindicated
we are finding i mean archaeologists
have discovered evidence of human uh
of human remains in south america
somewhere i don't remember where which
is about 130 000 years old
so that totally disproves this theory
this mainstream theory that human
habitation in in human presence in this
region is only about
13 14 000 years old
so i think his theories make a lot of
sense
and now they are gaining mainstream
acceptance grudgingly but slowly
right
so that's that shows what nonsense these
mainstream historians have been peddling
for such a long time
for such a long time it's just dogma
even though there is evidence staring
you in the face like the almec statues
for instance in south america there are
these giant olmec statues which are
several thousand years old they depict
people with uh
with african features
not asian features
so it looks like it was made by
ancient humans who may have traveled
from africa across the atlantic ocean
southern atlantic ocean and made their
way into southern america
now again
the so that's one example which may have
happened many thousand years ago
and so on so forth so i think his
theories are very interesting he has
spoken about the amazon rainforest
about a super soil that was used there
so the amazon rainforest which is so
huge
looks like it was an artificially
planted garden
and
because the spaniards wiped out
the
civilizations of south america
and uh most of the people died out
because of
diseases these people had introduced
so then the jungle reclaimed all these
lands and today if you do
if you do a laser or radar lidar
analysis of the terrain you can find
structures hidden below beneath the
forest
so
his theories make a lot of sense he says
that human civilization is actually very
old much older than what we think
maybe
may way older than ten thousand years
before today and so on so his theories
make a lot of sense
his theories are based upon on on actual
evidence and facts
and i think in the future it's going to
become mainstream
so
i'm really happy for him that he has
been vindicated he had been ridiculed
for like more than two decades as a
pseudo-historian and a crazy guy but
well that's not the case so yeah it
makes a lot of sense
okay bharat chandra says
[Laughter]
are they mental our former prime
ministers exposing our
intelligence agents raw agents in
pakistan i can't imagine the horrific
tortures they may have gone through
why would any sane person give out the
information of your own agents
to the enemy country
so as far as i know there have been two
indian prime ministers who have done
this
the first one was shri
muraji desai
and the second one was shri uh
ik
was prime minister for three months in
the 1990s three months
approximately three months
and mister what's his name uh the other
guy
muradji desai was prime minister for a
short period of time one or two years
something like that
in the 1980s late 70s or early 80s some
somewhere like that i don't remember i
have never found these people
interesting so i've not studied their
lives in detail so i can't place the
exact time frame late 70s or early 80s
that's no that's morality they say most
likely late seventies
so what mr murady this i did
was
yeah i think uh ziyal huck was the
pakistani dictator at the time
the dictator of pakistan so what muraji
decided was that he said i he declared
that i want peace with peace with
pakistan and we will not do anything
that will harm our relations of
relations with pakistan
and therefore what he did was he
disclosed all the identities and
locations of india's intelligence assets
raw agents in pakistan to the pakistanis
but the pakistanis did not reciprocate
and they did not disclose identities of
their agents in india it was a
unilateral gesture that was not
reciprocated and mr murray this i was
perfectly happy with it
similarly in the 1990s mr ike gujral who
was prime minister for all of three
months did the same thing
he disclosed i don't know if he
disclosed but he wound up he stopped
supporting
all the
indian intelligence agents the entire
network in pakistan i'm sure they were
all caught
and one can
imagine what sort of atrocities and
tortures they must have undergone
if any of them are still alive they will
be languishing in pakistani jails and
they will stay there forever essentially
now
why would an indian prime minister prime
minister do such a thing
this is something that has been this is
something that hurts india's long-term
national interest because we want to
know what's happening in pakistan
it is
it is in our favor in our benefit if we
know if we get gather intelligence from
pakistan from pakistani territory if we
have intelligence assets embedded deep
in inside pakistani society
that's what every country does that's
what the israelis do that's what the
russians do that's what the americans do
that's how
state craft that's how trade craft is
played so why would an indian prime
minister expose and destroy india's
intelligence network in pakistan
i mean one could
ascribe this to
to stupidity maybe he was stupid he
don't understand he did not understand
what he was doing but when you are at
this position of prime minister
you can't be stupid
a stupid person cannot become a prime
minister
so
the only other
thing you can say is that this was an
anti-national act
it was an action an act that harmed
india's long-term national interests and
an action such as that can only be
termed an anti-national action
so we had two prime ministers who were
anti-nationals and coincidentally
i don't know about mr gujarat
but mr murray this i was a lifelong
guess what
he was a lifelong
gandhian
he was a devotee of
mohandas gandhi
he called himself a gandhian
and mr gandhi is well known for his
unilateral concessions
to foreign powers to the british
to the rioters
to the terrorists to the moplas
to the
butchers
of
kolkata 1946 direct action day
right
he would give these unilateral
concessions to all these people but he
would never do anything for the actual
people of india for the mainstream
population of india
so many
unilateral concessions against the
indian national interest
so this is something that mr gandhi used
to do and this is something mr
muraji this i continued in the same
tradition
and even mr gujarat did the same thing
so that's the kind of leaders we had
which is why i keep saying if india
will succeed in the long term it will
succeed only if we
produce
good leaders and if we promote the right
the good leaders to the to the highest
positions
leadership is what matters
you may be the
best society in the world you may be the
most prosperous nation in the world but
if you have poor leadership it's all
going to collapse like a pack of cards
it's all about leadership
aranya raj says is it true
that the hindi language and hindustani
music was created by the turkic invaders
the turkic invaders spoke various turkic
languages like the chagatai language and
various other turkic languages
so why would they create a new language
for india i mean what what would they
gain from it
so no the hindi language was not created
by the turks
hindustani music i mean would these guys
were nomads
they lived a nomadic lifestyle
in central asia they never stayed in one
place they would move from one place to
another they lived in tents
they had no culture to speak of
do you think a tradition as profound as
indian classical music
with thousands of ragas that are so
profound and so ancient do you think
a bunch of ragtag
half wild nomads
would have the intellectual capacity to
create a tradition like that
i mean it makes no sense whatsoever
so indian classical music has been
developed in india over several thousand
years many thousand years it's the
oldest known musical tradition in the
history of humanity
and the hindi language is
a language that's native to india the
so-called urdu language urdu whatever
the hell you call it that is a mongrel
half breed language that is a
combination of
hindi grammar and some hindi vocabulary
which is mixed up with turkic words
persian words and arabic words
it is
a an inferior mongrel language
with a lot of foreign contamination
but it's essentially the same as hindi
because you call bollywood the hindi
film industry it's actually the urdu
urdu film industry
so urdu has become mainstream
mainstreamed in india because of
bollywood
so that's why all these strange notions
and beliefs have crept in into indian
society that maybe the turks did us a
great favor by creating the hindi
language
and giving us hindustani music which is
not the case which is not the case at
all
rudra mahadeva says
i feel frustrated with the amount of
corruption in every area of government
law and order and judiciary system i
feel like
like leaving india forever for other
great opportunities because i feel
bharat doesn't want to be prosperous
again
i feel that as if i as an individual
doesn't don't matter in india's future
what should i do
i want to see india prosperous again but
i don't trust the indian political
system
your sentiment is shared by
millions of people in india lots of
people leave india because of this
region no reason
the belief is that the people of india
are the cause of this
which is not the case it is the indian
system the
the indian governance system the
government the institutions are nothing
but the british raj it has never been
dismantled
so these institutions
the
bureaucrats the officials they act as if
they are
officials of a foreign occupying power
if they give you justice it's as a favor
to you you don't deserve it you can't
ask for it you can't demand it it's not
your right it is something they give to
you as a gift
if they give you any service in india
it's it's it's a favor that they bestow
upon you that is the attitude of any
government official go to any government
office even the smallest petty little
official will have that attitude right
so that is a
that is a the legacy of the british raj
which we never removed after
independence after dominion status
right after 47
and the education system again
victimizes students and so on so forth
so it is a sentiment that you see
everywhere people want to see india
great again india want to see india
prosperous again but the system doesn't
want that the system is designed
to keep india
under some kind of foreign occupation as
if india was still occupied by a foreign
power
it wants to keep indian
uh the india citizens
oppressed
and suppressed
it it stifles every
attempt to innovate and do something
good for the country
so it is a system that has created the
situation
so what you should do i mean i'm
assuming you're a youngster
uh more than half of my viewers are
below the age of 25 so i'm assuming
you're a youngster what i would say is
get the hell out of the country
i'm not saying go away forever i'm
saying that if you really want to
contribute to india
go see the world go gain experience
in whatever field whatever
industry
you're going to be good at
go work abroad get lots of experience
make something of yourself acquire some
genuine skills become wealthy
and then come back to india and try to
change the system
because i i hope that in the next 10 20
years india will change significantly
there are reforms been being implemented
i am
obviously i would like to see that the
pace of reforms be much faster
we need to reform all india's
institutions
the bureaucracy
judiciary
the government system the constitution
the laws everything needs to be
overhauled it will take time
so if you are a youngster go out of the
country leave the country for 10 20
years
make something of yourself become
wealthy become powerful
acquire skills acquire experience and
expertise then come back to india
and
contribute what you can
so that's what i would say i will never
advise people
especially capable talented people to
stay back in india as a youngster
because if you are earning
10 000 rupees a month you can't change
the nation but if you are earning a
million dollars a month you can
certainly change the nation so first go
elsewhere make your fortune
make something of yourself then come
back in and contribute to the country
that's what i would
suggest
anita says do we really require such a
long constitution or would a small
consideration like that of the us be
better for us
so let's understand what a constitution
is
a constitution is not the legal system
it's not a set of laws it is a set of
guidelines
which tell you how the country is to be
run so the laws are all based upon these
guidelines
right the code of laws of any country is
based on the constitution of the country
a country like the uk for instance
doesn't have a constitution
which is a special case because it's a
it's a monarchy actually
so a constitution is a set of guidelines
that tell you how what are the what are
the guiding principles of the country
what is the value system what is the
culture what is the civilization
what are the values what are the
principles and so on that's what the
constitution actually outlines
now india's consideration is something
not even a constitutional expert
actually understands
you ask any two constitutional experts
and they will have a lot of differences
about the way they interpret india's
constitution i think the indian
constitution is one of the longest
constitutions in the world
full of schedules and chapters and god
knows what
nobody has ever read the constitution in
full
it has more than 500 pages if i am not
mistaken
the american constitution has seven
pages
a school child
can understand the u.s constitution it
is actually taught in
i don't know sixth grade seventh grade
right
it is something every child can
understand
and it makes it very clear what kind of
country the us is
and again the amendments to the u.s
constitution are very few and far
between in india the constitution is
amended every other day
we have had more than 100 at least 100
amendments to the indian constitution
including some amendments during the the
emergency
when the words
secular and
socialist were inserted illegally
in the preamble of the constitution so
the constitution
doesn't serve in in india in any way
it simply complicates matters
it is a foreign constitution it espouses
and promotes foreign values western
values it is explicitly hindu phobic
in articles 25 to 30 i think and so on
and so forth why do we need such such a
constitution
reject it india needs to move beyond
that india needs a new constitution
a constitution that is rooted and
grounded in indian cultural and
civilizational values
that's what india needs
in other words india needs a dharmic
constitution a new one
so countries uh change their
constitution all the time sri lanka is
right now undergoing a process of of
writing a new constitution why can't we
do it the thing is it serves the
politicians
it keeps the country divided and that is
of great benefit
to politicians who espouse soft
separatism like the
like the uh dravidian parties in
southern india
various other political outfits
mainstream outfits in northern india etc
and so on and so forth so all of this
actually benefits politicians and then
that's why they don't want the
constitution to be discarded
but if india is to
rise again
as a true civilization we need to change
the constitution and that is something
that will benefit every single citizen
of the country
so that that's what should happen
eventually
okay aditi says um
our body is sat guru says our body is
just a heap of memory
if today i as an indian start living in
china eating their foods my features
won't change because body remembers
i might not consciously know my seventh
grade grandmother but i may have her
nose
when we all have a similar origin that
of africa why do we look so different
okay i'm not sure of what uh mr sadhguru
has said but okay assuming what he has
said
so the main question is if if we all
originate from africa why do we look so
different all of us
which is a good question
uh so the best
to to our best knowledge
we are a species that originated in
africa i mean the data that we have all
of it it it points to that
of course in the future if we have new
discoveries new data then that story may
change it's a story that keeps changing
as you find more data
but so far it is
it is uh
widely
accepted that our origin as a species is
in the continent of africa and from
there the latest migration out of africa
was about 70 75 000 years ago
which is the origin of all
non-african humans who are living on the
planet today including me including
indians chinese asians europeans etc
so
if we were all africans originally why
do we all look so different it's called
evolution and adaption
see it's like this
if i were to spend a day on the beach
shirtless
from morning till evening
by evening my skin will be three or four
shades darker
because i'm exposed to sunlight
in india if if you do it in india it's
especially true because india is in the
tropical zone so you have more sunlight
pouring in
and so
in in the course of 8 to 10 hours my
skin will be two or three shades darker
it happens very quickly now if i were to
live in let's say somewhere in deep
southern india tamil nadu kerala and if
my family was to live there for like 10
20 generations
or let's say five centuries
i think it will become
an evolutionary adaption that we will
all gain darker skin
because since you are getting so much
exposed so much more exposure to
sunlight the body needs to protect
itself from that by creating more
melanin and eventually that memory is
transferred to the genes
and that's why you get darker skin if a
person
from southern india
if a person who has dark skin for
instance where to move
if a family of dark-skinned people were
to move to the northern latitudes let's
say in
let's say in mongolia
or or let's say even punjab kashmir etc
and they live there for
20 30 40 generations they will acquire
lighter skin because you need a certain
amount of sunlight to absorb sufficient
vitamin d
so it's all evolution adaption you adapt
you evolve and humans evolve
over time
people who live in uh
in in regions of asia
siberia etc where there is so much snow
there is so much snow that the glare of
slow snow can blind you it can cause
snow blindness so then if you live in
such a region your body will eventually
adapt to make your eyes smaller so that
less sunlight comes in
so that is an adaption
to
uh
offset the the possibility of snow
blindness and so on and so forth so
that's why we have evolved over time
it it doesn't take very long to evolve
maybe 10 20 30 generations is sufficient
to see a significant change
in in characteristics
so people who live in northern europe
people who live in
northern asia
they have significantly lighter skin
because these regions receive very less
sunlight compared to what you would
receive in
indonesia
southern asia
the indian subcontinent africa etc so
that's why you see all this all these
diverse
features and characteristics
so that is the reason why even though we
are all
originally from africa if you go back
seven to eight thousand years we still
look so different because we have
because in the past there was no
easy traveling today you can just hop
onto a plane and travel anywhere you
want in the world right today you can do
that
in the past
communities were isolated for centuries
or even millions thousands of years
millennia
especially if you lived in uh
isolated regions in high valleys in in
in the sub-arctic regions etc you would
be isolated there for thousands of years
and that's why you would
develop
uh very characteristic features
so that is the reason why you have all
these
different
uh
what is it called it's called phenotypes
i think you know different uh
appearances of different ethnicities and
different geographical regions that's
the reason why we see this
okay mao ji says will you shed light on
the parsi community's role in the opm
export from india to china
it's an interesting question so who are
the parties the parsis are uh
they are migrants
refugees their ancestors were refugees
from iran from persia
when the
invasion of persia happened
the the
the arabic
invasion of persia happened
uh the country of persia was very very
quickly and brutally converted to the
religion of the arabs right
this happened over the course of 20 20
30 years very rapid change
and the people the original religion or
culture of persia was zoroastrianism
which is a
which is a form which is one which is
descended from ancient hinduism right
so that was the original religion of the
persians now they were all converted to
the religion of the arabs now some
people were unwilling to give up the
religion and the culture so they escaped
from persia and the only place where
they thought of escaping to
was the old homeland of the persians
which is india so they went by boat
and they reached the western coast of
gujarat which is
yeah the western coast of gujarat
where they were
very kindly very magnanimously given
refuge by the local king of gujarat
and they were allowed to continue
worshiping their gods and continue
practicing their customs the traditions
the only conditions were that they were
to adopt indian dress indian dressing
style and they were to start speaking
the local language which was gujarati
and that is the story of the parsees
now
the thing is very strange
uh the strange thing is that for
they they came to india more than a
thousand years ago
more than about 1200 or so years ago
roughly
and until the british occupation of
india the parties were
almost completely anonymous
they lived in southern gujarat mostly
and they did not achieve anything of any
significance
they were
one of the well
almost unknown communities
in this region
so they did not achieve anything
spectacular they did not
excel
in any discipline like trade or anything
but after the british occupied india
the parcel suddenly became superstars
right
so what happened was that the british
did this
as part of their policy to divide and
rule
so they were in the process of
disastrously impoverishing india of
rendering india destitute
but
they decided to because the parsees were
foreigners
they were the descendants of foreigners
so the british decided to give them
special treatment
so they gave them special privileges and
permissions to start doing certain
trades which had been destroyed in india
for instance the british had destroyed
the ship building trade in india
but they allowed the parcels to take up
the trade so the parcels became ship
builders they were given given other
privileges that were withheld from other
indians
and that's how the parsis began again
began succeeding in trade and commerce
and all that
it was all artificial in nature
right so that's what happened now when
the british
uh started trading with china they were
they were buying chinese tea
because there was this big craze in in
in britain and in europe and in the west
for chinese tea
now to buy chinese tea you had to give
money to the chinese but that would
impoverish the british because they only
wanted to extract wealth out of india
and possibly from china
so this strategy they hit upon was to
cultivate opium in india instead of food
crops
in great quantities
and then to sell that opium to china in
exchange for tea
instead of selling uh instead of buying
tea in exchange for silver
this caused a great deal of strife in
china
millions of chinese became opm addicts
the chinese emperor tried to fight back
against this then there were the opium
wars and the chinese were humiliated
by the british by the americans and so
on it's it's not just one nation but the
british were the main drivers
so they forced indians in the region of
malwa i think to cultivate opium
instead of food food crops
this contributed to the famines that the
british were engineering in in india
so opium was grown in india it was
transported to china and tea was taken
out of china and other goods were taken
out of china this impoverished china
and the traders who did this
who participated in this opm trade who
were at the forefront
of the opium trade where the power sees
individuals like that fellow what's his
name
uh jumpset gg boy
who became fabulously wealthy
so he was a drug dealer
then there were the ready money brothers
other party stooges who became extremely
rich
as a consequence of this trade in drugs
so the parsees took the opportunity to
become drug runners drug dealers
and they became fabulously wealthy as a
consequence
and then they they restyled themselves
as philanthropists and all that
and they started
giving money donating money to construct
buildings this is the jj school of arts
in bombay mumbai
is named after jump set gigi boy the
drug dealer
and various other things this guy uh
kovas ji or whatever his name ready
money
so this ready money guy in the 19th
century when india was going through
terrible famines which were created by
the british he was extremely wealthy and
he donated
lacks of rupees
lots of money
to to the british to create monuments in
england
right so that's why they called him
ready money because it was always at the
service
of the british
so that is how the policies became so
fabulously wealthy
and that's the origin of all these big
parsley companies that's why the parsees
are so are so rich today
because they
profited benefited from this trade in
drugs and other things right
so that is the story
so all this money that the person today
it is believe that the partisans are
exceptional people they succeeded where
all the other indians failed that is not
the case
if they were so exceptional what were
they doing before the british came to
india they did nothing exceptional
before that
right so it is a clear case of social
engineering the the good old divide and
rule strategy of the british
so all the parsi money
comes from this
this this activity
uh because of the special preferences
given to the given to them by the
british and because of the trade in
drugs in opium
with china
and that's why the chinese have this uh
they they hold this grudge against india
because
because indian merchants these parsees
were at the forefront
of
the humiliation of the chinese during
this opium trade
that's
an interesting and
rather forgotten chapter of history
ishwara moody says what's your opinion
about the upi technology and other
should india be proud of this
can india promote upi through financial
diplomacy
so upi is a breakthrough technology
which the indian government created
other it is it is it is based on aadhaar
the unique identifier that every indian
has
and it has genuinely revolutionized
the entire
the way transactions financial
and economic transactions are done in
this country in india it has totally
revolutionized everything
see when this technology was first
rolled out when it was unveiled
people like what's his name
what's his name
chidambaram the former home minister etc
said that indians are poor indians don't
have mobile phones how will indians use
this
how wrong was he
every indian has a mobile phone today
and everybody uses upi people you i've
heard people use upi
uh to to purchase vegetables
for to purchase groceries
and so on to to give donations to
temples and so on and so forth so
everybody uses upi today india has
leapfrogged ahead of all other nations
in electronic transactions
monetary transactions it has gone far
far ahead of the second largest country
which is china far ahead
so it is a revolutionary technology it
is truly eventually going to make india
cashless a casual society it's going to
happen in the next 10 years or 20 years
i would say
at most
so it is something that has truly made
um
financial monetary transaction
transactions very easy to do
it has empowered the people of india i
think india should be very proud of it
surely and today other countries are
trying to emulate that other countries i
mean europe and the us and america
they are trying
to emulate what india has done
isn't that interesting
india has taken a leadership role in in
this matter
so i think india should be very proud of
it should india promote you to upi
through financial diplomacy sure let's
do it uh why not if it benefits india in
some way
the government can go ahead and do this
but india should be very proud of what's
happened of what's been achieved
there are two there are a couple two or
three or four things in the past few
years
half decade or so that have totally
transformed india one is upi and other
the second thing is cheap and reliable
and fast internet
india has the lowest data rates in the
world
it has truly empowered the people of
india it has truly connected india
together as a nation and with the world
india has the lowest rate per gb
of uh of internet data in the world
or one of the lowest rates and it's fast
and it's reliable today
so it's because of
private companies like uh
and airtel right
there's a reason why the mainstream
media india tries to demonize reliance
and adani and all that because they are
contributing to the growth of india
so that they demonize them termed them
as capitalists and crony capitalists and
all which is totally false
so you have fast internet you have upi
another and you have gst before gst you
had octroi which essentially reduced
india to a collection of independent
independent uh states
every time you send some goods across
state boundaries you had to pay
uh
this octo tax at every single state
boundary and you had
you had waiting queues
for four days on end so it made
transportation of goods across the
country almost impossible and that's why
the prices of goods were so high and so
on so gst has revolutionized that i
agree that some of the gst rates are
still too high because various political
parties ensured that happened but slowly
over time it will all become more
rational
so gst upi and other and
cheap
fast internet
these things have revolutionized india
in the last five years india is i think
on the brink of a major transformation
which we are not able to understand
because it's happening in real time
but if you will look back 10 20 years
from today you will realize how big a
monu and how monumental this
transformation is india is truly
uh
transforming what it is
so
it's good it's great india should be
proud of it
okay ishwar roshan says which is a
better form of developing a city
horizontal development expanding land
use or vertical development building
skyscrapers
should india switch to vertical
development from the present horizontal
style
as india's population is rising with a
limited geographical area of our country
this is a very interesting question so
historically india has had
horizontal development
you have towns villages cities that are
that expand horizontally in the past we
had excellent city planning town
planning during the saraswati hindu
phase of our history
and even later before the
turkic and european invasions of india
afterwards everything got destroyed
so india has traditionally had
horizontal development of course in the
saraswati hindu phase we had
multi-storied buildings that is
well-known two-story storage buildings
or maybe even more so we had that
technology 5000 years ago
but those were not skyscrapers like 30
40 50 storage buildings we didn't we did
not have that
at the time maybe the technology wasn't
there
today like you have very rightly
observed we have
a ridiculous growth of population we are
1.3 billion strong which is ridiculous
so clearly if we were to do horizontal
development it would be it would take up
all the land in the nation
and therefore it makes sense to go go
vertical and create
uh
skyscraper style residential buildings
which you see in all indian metros you
have these 10 story 20 storied
apartments
flat structure and all that in which
people live in these flats and these are
all
stacked vertically
so that is something we need to do right
now
hopefully in the future whenever
population is back under control then we
may be able to go back
to a more horizontal style of living
maybe a couple of centuries in the
future you have to plan long term as of
today it makes sense to have
more of this vertical
developmental style because we have no
option right now
of course we have to remember that
it is not natural for humans to live in
these vertical style buildings
it is always beneficial to live closer
to the ground closer to the earth
more connected with nature and all that
today india cities are all concrete
jungles which is kind of
sucking the joy out of people's lives
who live who live in metropolitan cities
hopefully this is a phase which will not
last very long maybe 100 200 years
but as of today yes it makes sense to
have
more of a vertical style of architecture
to
absorb the population of india and give
everybody
a
good housing to live in
harshit says asks what factors prevented
india from
having a renaissance in medieval times
okay let us define renaissance and let's
divide medieval times so when you talk
about medieval times it's usually about
the first half of the second millennium
so between about eleven twelve hundred
eighty
two fifteen sixteen seventeen hundred
eighty thereabouts right
that is roughly the medieval period
depending on which historian you ask
and what is the meaning of renaissance
the renaissance is a french word it
means rebirth
so a renaissance means a rebirth of the
country's culture of its economy
civilization and all that so the typical
classical example of renaissance is the
italian renaissance the french
renaissance all that
which happened in europe when europe
became exceptionally
fabulously rich as a result as a
consequence
of
its colonial activities
so that's when the european society
became very prosperous the merchants
became very rich and they started
investing in
the arts in culture
so you had all these sculptors and
artists like michelangelo
leonardo da vinci and so on who who
built all these who who
created these magnificent paintings and
sculptures that adorn
cities in italy
fiorentina florence
venice trieste etc
and this spread across europe so that's
a renaissance so europe was in the
throes of the dark ages
when it was tightly controlled by the
church by the catholic church vatican
and people were illiterate and
everything was in poverty etc and then
you had the renaissance when you had a
huge infusion of money of wealth
the average
prosperity levels rose significantly and
you had this flowering of culture so
that is a renaissance
factors prevented india from having a
renaissance undergoing renaissance in
the medieval times
so between 1100 and 1780 if you look at
the time period and let's let's call
that for instance the medieval times
then india was under foreign occupation
india was under turkic occupation
the turks were doing their best to
actively destroy indian culture they
destroyed all of india's universities
they destroyed
all of india's great temples in northern
india
thousands maybe tens of thousands of
temples were destroyed
all of india's great
cultural
and educational leaders professors
scholars all were murdered
indians were oppressed horribly there
were these mass conversion campaigns
which succeeded in afghanistan in
gandhar gandha has now become a separate
country afghanistan different culture
right
and so on so when you are under a
foreign occupation they are destroying
your culture and they're they're
siphoning off your money
and enriching themselves and and
impoverishing the population of the
country you can never have a renaissance
so that is the factor the only factor
the one factor
that prevented india from having a
renaissance
india was fabulously rich
and then the foreign occupations
happened because we were not united
and that's why there was no flowering of
culture the culture was actually
destroyed
much of india's culture has been
today as we as we speak
and that process continues today under
the secular socialist regime
and consideration and laws
so to have a renaissance of india to
have a new flowering of india's culture
what needs to happen first of all the
foreign constitution the foreign laws
the foreign government structure needs
to be thrown out
you need a constitution with indian
values
you need laws that are based in indian
values and indian culture
and you need a governance structure and
institutions like the judiciary etc that
are based in on in indian values
and that are accountable to the people
of india that is number one secondly we
need to expand our economy greatly
once the per capita gdp goes beyond ten
thousand dollars then you are a middle
income country and that's that's when
the expressions of culture will start
flowering and of course you need to
ensure that all the foreign interference
especially cultural interference in
india
should stop
there is
an enormous amount of foreign cultural
and religious
interference in india
billions of dollars of money is being
poured into india to carry out various
activities
right so all that needs to stop if we
can achieve all that
then we will have a new renaissance
in india we had many fake
episodes of renaissance in india the
so-called bengali cultural renaissance
which is
which is something india's historians
like to write about
you see when india's historians promote
something there's always something fishy
in it
bengals cultural
so-called cultural relations was
concerted efforts in attempts by certain
intellectuals
like ram mohandro etc
to reform hinduism
why do you need to reform hinduism
so that's the thing right so there was
there was a fake renaissance it was not
a real renaissance a real renaissance is
when you have grass roots flowering of
culture because of
a significant amount of prosperity so
that is something that will hopefully
happen in the next 50 years that's what
one can hope for
uh dominic says what is the future of
astronauts in india is there any scope
for astronauts in india or is the only
option america
well india does have a space program
india does have plans to uh to send
humans into space in the next two three
four five years sometime in that time
frame so we will have astronauts in
india soon one hopes
and they have
the government has stated that india
will eventually have its own space
station in orbit around the earth
and so on and so forth so yes there is
a scope for a limited number of
astronauts in the next 10 20 years
i think what needs to happen is that i
wish we need to encourage private actors
and private companies to venture into
space exploration like for instance what
spacex has done in the us
so spacex has completely revolutionized
the space uh industry in the u.s
they are on the brink in the next 10
years of wiping out the
lockheed martin and other companies the
united launch alliance because they are
so nimble they operate like a
startup they they do multiple launches
a month they have the capacity to do
that and they are always innovating
always building a more powerful and
better rocket the technologies they have
developed are they have developed them
at breakneck speed and very good
innovative technologies like the uh
reusable boosters and all that
and you don't see any of that innovation
in in india in israel because isro is
run by the government
and in israel the scientists and
engineers can't do anything without
approval from the government bureaucrats
or whoever it is who is overseeing
israel and
politicians and bureaucrats and other
officials they don't have any vision
they don't have any understanding of
science
of of technology of engineering
and that's why they're happy with the
little rockets we have today like the
pslv and the gslv those are little
rockets compared to what spacex is
building
and there's a spacex the company has
already built the dragon booster which
they used to ferry astronauts into
into earth orbit and so on so
there is a significant
scope in the future for
astronauts
in the us there's also virgin galactic
which uh
is offering space tourism services and
then you have blue origin which also has
a been able to go to send people into
space
so these are private companies very
nimble agile companies startups
essentially that are taking the lead in
the us so if india were to create the
right environment for private players to
succeed in space exploration then you
will have this field open up
and then you will have
opportunities in the next 20 30 years
for indians to become astronauts
without having to go to another country
you know so that could happen if we
change the system
and reform the system significantly
so that's what needs to happen
i hope it happens
because i know every youngster every kid
in the in in
in the world
wants to become an astronaut right they
want to go to space and experience
uh weightlessness space travel all that
so um today if you want to be an
astronaut in india you need to be a
fighter pilot you need to have that
expertise in the future it won't be
necessary i mean recently blue origin
sent up william shatner into space the
actor who played uh
captain kirk in star trek
and the the that guy is more than 90
years old today
and a 90 year old was able to travel to
space so you don't need exceptional
fitness or such abilities
i think almost anybody can be
sent into space once you have the
ability to launch people on a routine
basis
so as of today
there is not much scope unless you are a
fighter pilot unless you're part of the
indian air force as a fighter pilot
in the future if reforms happen there
may be more possibilities opening up
and i hope it happens
okay gayatri asks why is the indian
government not focusing on solar power
power we have abundant potential there
is the initial investment too expensive
so actually i would disagree with this
assessment that the government is not
focusing on solar power you may not be
aware of it
uh india is focusing significantly on
solar power there was this target of
of uh
creating a hundred giga gigawatts
of
solar electricity by
which year was it uh that target was
meant was met several years before it
was due so india is investing
significantly in solar energy and solar
power india is the founding member
the founder of the global solar alliance
which the latest entrant is the united
states so india is the leader globally
in this solar energy
initiative
and in the future india is going to
expand its solar energy solar
electricity capabilities many fold in
the next five to ten years so i think
india is one of the leaders in the world
when it comes to solar power and yes i
agree that it we can take it much much
further ahead than what it is being done
today the major in impediment when it
comes to india is that we are importing
90 of the solar panels
from other countries
we need to start building these panels
in india
then the prices will drop even further
and then we will be able to reach our
true full potential in
generating electricity from
solar power
so that's what needs to happen but india
is doing well thus far
okay this is going to be the final
question for today
yeshwanth says
why did persons like diana the saraswati
and swabi swami vivekananda criticize
our dharma
in our holy books the son is depicted as
a god who can talk etc
in spite of advancements in astronomy
why then this misconception okay i'm
going to answer the first question
uh
about the saraswati and swami
vivekananda criticizing dharma
so
let's talk about mr saraswati first he
was born i think
in gujarat
and uh then he spent his career
elsewhere
so you know
people tell me i mean i i had said that
he was so here's what we know about them
saraswati he founded the arya samaj i
think
which is uh which which
which champions a monotheistic form of
hinduism so it is a reform movement it
seeks to reform hinduism
and when you say you want to reform
hinduism
it is implicit that you believe that
hinduism is a backward and broken
religion or culture which is why it
needs reforms
right so then the saraswati was in favor
of a monotheistic form of hinduism
because he felt it was superior to the
polytheistic form of hinduism
which has been around for thousands of
years and he was against idol worship
murthy puja and so on and so forth
so here's the thing
i have not studied mr saraswati in any
great detail
i have not studied his book what is
called some prakash thing satyarth
prakash people tell me read this chapter
of prasad prakash and read that chapter
because it clarifies his vision i am not
interested
when i come across a person
like like a historical figure like
delano saraswati i look at the big
picture first i see what was his
philosophy
and the philosophy is extremely clear he
was a hinduism reformer he was against
murthy puja he was in favor of
monotheism when i see this big picture
it tells me i don't need to read any
further about his
philosophy about his writing because it
is an inferior thing
he is not
worth
investing my time in so what i can say
is that diana saraswati was somebody
with an inferiority complex he found
monotheism the abrahamic monotheisms
superior to hinduism that's why he tried
to transform hinduism into something
like the abrahamic religions he even
created a book so one god one book and
maybe he would be the prophet perhaps
you know
that sort of thing so i have no interest
in saraswati he was a mentally colonized
person with an inferiority complex i
know you some people are going to hate
me for saying this well
nothing new
so
so that's the reason why he criticized
dharma because he was a person with a
deep inferiority complex
now when it comes to swami vivekananda
when it comes to swami vivekananda i
have again
not studied his life in great detail i
have not studied his writings in great
detail here is the thing guys you know
it's like this
when india's historians
portray somebody as being great
it sets off warning bells in my head
there is this so-called historian these
days some woman
this individual odd something who is
portraying or aurangzeb is a great great
great king of india right
and indian textbook also in the past
they depicted aurangzeb as a great pious
man as a pious leader
and so on
so when they portray somebody as good
when they portray tripu sultan
the butcher of mysore as being a great
freedom fighter it sets off alarm bells
in your head in my head at least
and same for ram mohan roy the portrait
game is a great reformer
well we now know the truth about this
guy ramon roy now again i have seen
since i was a little kid that swami
vivekananda has been extolled by india's
historians now i am not saying he was
bad or anything i'm not saying that
because i have not studied him
i have simply never found him
interesting enough to study his writings
what we know is that he was initially
influenced by the brahma-samaj which is
ramahandra's creation
then he went into some other aspects of
spirituality he was deeply influenced by
western thought
right
and then he became famous for giving a
speech in english in america about
hinduism i'm sure he had very good
intentions and maybe he was a great
spiritual leader or whatever it is but i
have never found him interesting enough
to study him
and i have heard stories that i'm i'm
not sure if they are right i've heard uh
i've read
uh
reports of him consuming meat and
advocating that if you travel outside of
india then it's okay to eat certain
kinds of meat and all that
so all of these things if i put together
it has made me very reluctant and very
uninterested in studying swami
vivekananda's
life story and his writings and his
philosophy and all that i have never
found him interesting enough i mean when
you talk about lord krishna he is a
monumental person very interesting
person
i want to study his whole entire life
when it comes to lord rama great person
he achieved so much he changed the lives
of millions of people same with lord
krishna he changed the entire fortunes
of the subcontinent of india
when it comes to somebody like vardham
and mahavira he impacted millions of
lives when you talk about gotham buddha
whether you agree with
both the dharma or not he is a very
significant figure who has touched the
lives of millions hundreds of millions
of people worldwide even today
right
when you talk about uh when you talk
about
adi shankara again a monumental figure
you know what the achievements are when
you talk about aha by holder we know
what a saintly great lady she was we
know what her achievements were
she touched the lives of millions in a
very positive way so when i compare
swami vivekananda with that i'm i
am left asking myself what where is the
achievements
and therefore i have never found him
interesting enough to study
and i have heard that he has criticized
hindu dharma which shows that he also
had this reformist mindset
now i today if people tell me to study
him i am actually afraid to study him
because i may find things
that i will have to speak about and then
people will hate me more
so i you know what
i just don't find him interesting enough
to study that's that's that's the real
truth
just i'm telling you honestly and
transparently i have never found swami
vivekananda interesting enough to study
maybe he was great maybe i'm i'm not so
maybe i'm not intellectually evolved
enough perhaps to find him interesting
maybe it is a deficiency in me
so everybody has deficiencies it could
be a deficiency of mine that i don't see
the greatness that everybody else sees
so if it is
that that if that is the case then i
accept it
as being my deficiency but i don't find
him interesting enough i find him having
the same traits of trying to reform
hinduism
as ram mohan roy had and then saraswati
had not to that extent but certainly he
had some reformist tendencies and when
you say you want to reform hinduism you
are
you are clearly implying that hinduism
is inferior and it is broken it needs to
be changed why do we need to change
this tradition that is more than ten
thousand years old hinduism doesn't need
reforms
it needs revival it needs to be
unchained it is right now being
oppressed and destroyed
it just needs to be left alone
it needs a revival not reforms
that's what i have to say about this now
let's take a look at some of the live
comments i'll take a few of the live
comments
okay let me see
[Music]
um
hey marathi says do you really think
innovation is a must for scientists or
astrophysicists
science is all about innovation it's
about understanding with what we
currently don't understand without
innovation there is no science
no astrophysics no cosmology no
theoretical physics there is no
advancement in science without
innovation if you don't innovate you're
just gonna teach the same old tired
stories
so yes
we need that
we need to know without innovation there
will be no science
i can already see some comments about
vivekananda g
to be expected
okay
soft power i have no interest in soft
power india needs to increase its hard
power
good question good question see to
soft power it doesn't really make any
real impact in the world unless it is
backed up
by hard power economic and military
power that's what india needs
sahil says uh
modi prime minister modi has already
announced an indian space association
for private players to enter into space
programs and work with isro what i am
talking about is different
what what this thing is going to do is
you're going to have lots of
private companies that will provide
supply spare parts
and other components to isro in making
satellites and rockets what i am talking
about is a new radical startup industry
in which companies start building
rockets from the ground up
so you're creating a private isro which
does everything in-house that's what i'm
talking about that is where the real
innovation happens
because when you are clear let's say
you're building a car and you're
sourcing components from 78 different
companies
it's going to be a nightmare to
integrate that all together all the
components need to fit together all the
softwares need to talk to each other
properly in the same language it's a
nightmare
but if you build everything in house
and if you're a startup with less money
then you try to optimize every rupee
that you have and you know you try to
make everything as optimized as possible
that's where the innovation comes from
so the indian space association is a
welcome step step a very good step but i
am talking about something radically
different
we need to create the right environment
for startup entrepreneurship in india
right
the kind of environment that would that
would uh empower
an indian version of elon musk for
instance
into creating an indian version of
spacex
hopefully ideally three four different
companies like that that compete and
collaborate
and that is going to be beneficial for
the country as a whole that's what we
need to look for
right do we have anything else
how useful are transfers of technologies
is what usonor asks well it depends
or it depends who is transferring to
whom
if there is a transfer of technology
from spacex to tesla it is essentially
in-house transfer of technology and
therefore the transfer of technology is
going to be full and complete
so for instance you have a transfer of
technology from
tesla
to the to the uh
solar company that elon musk has
so tesla is an innovator in
manufacturing battery packs lithium iron
lithium-ion batteries that power the
tesla cars
so the same technology is also used in
the solar company that elon musk has so
that transfer of technology is complete
and full but when it comes to transfer
of military technology military
technology from one country to another
there's always going to be something
that they will hold back
first of all it will cost a lot of money
let's say we want a transfer of
technology jet engine technology from
france to india i hear there is
something going on some kind of project
between the french aerospace company
snecma
and hindustan aeronautics aeronautics
limited
the kaveri engine that has been in
development for 783 years or something
like that
so uh
some technology transfer will happen
maybe we will have a work recovery
engine finally
but they will not transfer the best
technology
it would it would not be in their
interest to do that right
so it all depends on who is transferring
the technology to whom and also what is
the nature of the technology being
transferred for instance if the french
have been able to perfect miniaturized
nuclear reactors for submarines
they will never transfer the technology
to any other country
even a country like india with whom they
have a very strong
and very uh trust trusting
strategic alliance they will still not
transfer the technology even if you pay
any amount of money so it can be useful
depending on the context the kind of
technology being transferred and the two
participants the giver and the taker the
seller and the buyer
it depends
okay my views are about somebody or the
other listen
um
people don't matter people are not
important the the
okay let me take up this question where
is it
okay my view is about rajiv the chit ji
listen i don't know much about raja
dikshitar g after i started doing this q
a sessions lots of people spoke to me i
mean they in the comments they have
spoken about mr rajiv dikshit so i
looked it up and
he is somebody who unfortunately passed
away
rather young
and it looks like he was a visionary
leader somebody who had a very good
vision for india
he died tragically young
so i think he was a very good leader he
had very good ideas i believe i have not
listened to his speeches his lectures i
am very short of time
i have to be very very very selective in
what
books i read what material i consume i
don't have time
you know so i i don't know much about
about his uh
his uh
his speeches his his writings etc if
they may be around but the impression
that i get is get is that he was a very
patriotic
and dedicated person it's it's rather
tragic that he
passed away so early
okay so
so yeah
that's what i have to say about this
i want to merge astrophysics with the
ancient indian scriptures which
scripture should i start with you cannot
merge modern astrophysics with ancient
indian scriptures the knowledge that was
available to our ancestors three
thousand four thousand years ago
it is nothing like the knowledge we have
today they had none of the data that we
have today they did not know about
cosmic micro background radiation they
did not know cmbr they did not know what
gamma ray burst they did not know about
quasars pulsars
99 of the information that we have today
was not available to our ancient
ancestors so in the scriptures they do
talk about concepts like gravitation
there are astronomical observations
there is a great deal of mathematics
that is the foundation of all science
today
so we had this great philosophical and
scientific tradition
but you cannot learn astrophysics or
merge astrophysics with that
ancient indian scriptures were mainly
philosophical treatises philosophy
with some elements of science
with
in some cases a lot of science a lot of
science in some cases
but
but you can't mix philosophy
and science in the modern context
in the 21st century context so you can't
try to talk about let's say
consciousness and astrophysics
because consciousness is not a
scientific concept you can't talk about
the supreme creator and the law of karma
with astrophysics you can't you simply
can't
astrophysics and science deals with
observable phenomena and observable
and physical objects
not about spiritual
or metaphysical or philosophical
concepts right
so
i would say that you should definitely
study india's ancient scriptures you
will learn so much from them they will
enrich your life beyond what you can
even imagine
but you can't merge astrophysics with
them it's a separate
discipline completely separate
discipline
right
okay
it's nearly two hours i think i will
stop now
thank you everybody for this wonderful
session thank you for all the wonderful
questions you keep asking me i got
hundreds
of brilliant questions i was only able
to cover about 25 30 of them today
please keep asking me questions i will
do my best to cover all of your
questions and answer all of them let's
keep doing this so tomorrow we will have
a live chat session
in which i will take live chat questions
and let's end it for today i will see
you tomorrow lovely talking to you all
thank you so much for your support for
your
viewership i am very very grateful more
grateful than you can imagine
thank you very much i will see you
tomorrow bye